Vaibhav Beohar Data Scientist

Vaibhav Beohar

<u>vbeohar@berkeley.edu</u> ● 437-343-7743 ● Toronto ON ● <u>https://www.linkedin.com/in/beohar/</u> ● <u>https://github.com/vbeohar/</u>

Skilled professional with experience in software engineering (front-end and back-end), data science, finance & accounting. Currently working as a data scientist at McKinsey. Obtained an MBA in 2012 and master's in data science from UC Berkeley

SKILLS

Languages: Python, Java, C++, SQL

Front end scripting languages: HTML5, JavaScript, JSON, CSS, jQuery, AJAX, D3.js, React.js

Risk/Planning & Analysis, Corporate Finance, Stakeholder management, Business Analysis

Libraries: TensorFlow, Keras, PyTorch, sklearn, NumPy, seaborn, pandas, Spacy, Transformers, Java Enterprise Edition (J2EE)

Applications and tools: MongoDB, MySQL, Oracle, Snowflake, PostgreSQL, SQLite, Nginx, Gunicorn, Anaplan, Docker containers, Bootstrap, Visual Basic, Google Cloud, AWS, DataBricks, GitHub, Heroku, MS Office, Atlassian Jira, Trello

Competencies: Full stack development, Design Patterns, Object Oriented Programming, Agile with Scrum, Exploratory Data Analysis, Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing (NLP), Deep Learning, Data Engineering, Financial Modeling,

EDUCATION

University of California Berkeley; School of Information

Master of Information & Data Science (MIDS) – GPA 3.97

Berkeley, CA August 2022

- Coursework data engineering, statistics, applied machine learning, causal inference & experiments, deep learning on edge devices, natural learning processing with deep learning, data visualization, capstone
- Projects:
 - Performed Airbnb price prediction using XGBoost, AutoML, neural network & logistic regression
 - o Trained deep learning models on IBM cloud and performed inference on Nvidia Jetson TX2 edge devices
 - Created full-stack website using JavaScript, Bootstrap, Flask and Python to display "social network" graph visualizations for the Star Wars movie franchise using D3.js
 - Explored Aspect Based Sentiment Analysis (ABSA) techniques and implemented fine-tuning of RoBERTa, SpanBERT and DistillBERT models to achieve material improvements in aspect extraction and classification tasks
 - Capstone project Created an end-to-end content recommendation analytics product called "MakeSense", to allow emerging streamers on Twitch expand their presence on the platform.
 - Technologies: Python, Flask, PostgreSQL/SQLite, jQuery/Ajax, D3.js, Nginx and Gunicorn, BERT model double fine-tuned on Masked Language Modeling (MLM) and Sentiment Classification tasks

University of Massachusetts Amherst; Isenberg School of Management

Master of Business Administration (MBA) Finance & Accounting – GPA 3.82

Amherst, MA May 2012

• Internship (June - Aug 2011): Goldman Sachs — Investment Accounting/Controllers (Jersey City, NJ)

Rajiv Gandhi Technological University

Bhopal, India

Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Science (Honors) - GPA 3.75

June 2004

EXPERIENCE

MCKINSEY & COMPANY

Toronto, ON March 2017– ongoing

Data Science Specialist

- Created an unsupervised information extraction NLP model using Python and Google's Universal Sentence Encoder on TensorFlow and Nvidia K100 GPU to implement an internal search engine for McKinsey's client documents and match them with prospective service line offerings using Snowflake, Python, Flask, jQuery and D3.js
- Performed monthly run of random forest and logistic regression based supervised learning models on R Studio and Python to evaluate McKinsey's 2000+ active/lost clients and create distribution of *most likely* service line offerings with 90% AUC
- Built asynchronous Flask server based natural language processing (NLP) model for sematic information extraction and use-case

Vaibhay Beohar Data Scientist

- ranking using MongoDB, Word2Vec, EventRegistry API and Python. Used Python multiprocessing code and a multi-compute environment to reduce latency by 80%
- Worked on machine learning models to predict headcount attrition, workforce monthly utilization, regional opex targets, cash reserves and various other key metrics; and integrating the results into the annual budgeting/planning software, Anaplan (a cloud based EPM platform) for firmwide distribution and user engagement
- Supervised, coordinated and lead discussions on various ad hoc data science discussions and prospective engagements using project management skills, Agile (with scrum) methodologies and tools such as Jira
- Key technologies and skills Python, Jupyter Notebook, R Studio, regression and supervised learning, SQL, NLP, MongoDB, PostgreSQL, word2vec, BERT, Spacy, jQuery and D3.js, Ubuntu, shell scripting

GLOBAL ATLANTIC FINANCIAL GROUP

Boston, MA

Associate – Risk, Planning & Analysis

May 2012- March 2017

- Prepared finance materials for CFO, monthly operating committee meetings, quarterly board and risk meetings and other adhoc projects, with timely analysis of various business lines for corporate finance decision making
- Automated legacy Excel models using VBA Macro and SQL for planning, budgeting, and forecasting of short-term and long-term net income of 8 sub- and 1 consolidated entity (\$52bn assets and >300mm operating income); leading to 95% reduction in execution/delivery time compared to prior forecasting models
- Overviewed Actual-to-Expected (A-to-E) variance analysis by cross-functional collaboration with controllers, actuarial, tax and expense teams and by mapping model-to-ledger income statement and balance sheet accounts
- Identified market, regulatory, accounting, and operational items impacting excess capital availability, including:
 - What-if scenario analysis with low/high/baseline test cases and KPIs reported on capital, OpEx and CapEx
 - Risk charges owing to business, interest rate, asset risks, reinsurance, hedges and derivatives
 - \$2bn+ Capital attribution analysis by new business, new sales, net investment income (NII) etc.

GOLDMAN SACHS New York, NY

Senior Consultant Programmer *April 2007– Aug 2010*

- Developed client-side portfolio management portal (http://360.gs.com) and various trading tools for Goldman Sachs Asset Management (GSAM) division using advanced Java, Unix, Perl, shell scripts, Sybase SQL and various open-source technologies
- Designed and developed a real-time trading solution, as well as an advanced risk model, with timely rollout during the critical Troubled Asset Relief Program (TARP) to assist the fixed-income trading desk with mortgage-backed security trading, portfolio tracking and performance monitoring tasks using IT tools
- Decommissioned and replaced legacy systems with consolidated web-based system for fixed income insurance desk
- Interacted with external vendors (such as Interactive Data BondEdge) for integrating 3rd party applications for GSAM portfolio management and reporting needs
- Developed, tested, and supported core modules for rollout of GSAM's fixed income insurance advisory system

SIGMA SOFTWARE SOLUTIONS

Pune, India / Toronto, ON

Senior Software Engineer

July 2004- Dec 2007

- Lead 4-member offshore team on various order, revenue & customer management enterprise level technology initiatives using advanced Java, J2EE, Unix, MySQL, open-source tools (CVS, Apache Struts, JUnit, Hibernate ORM)
- Developed, researched, and documented technical project artifacts and software design documents
- Lead a "first in company" novel proof of concept of an end-to-end enterprise web-based system using Hibernate object relational mapping framework for an Africa based telecom client. Customer was highly appreciative of the effort and was engaged in long-term contract
- Underwent a 4-week companywide intensive bootcamp on advanced Java. Stood 1st out of 35 trainees

CERTIFICATIONS

Chartered Financial Analyst (level I) and "Official Anaplan Developer" certification